Inventory of the Papers of Zelda Nordlinger, 1969 (1970-1977) 1998
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Papers of Zelda Nordlinger 1969 (1970-1977) 1998
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
98N75
1,192 items (3 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the library by Zelda Nordlinger in October of 1998.
Biographical/Historical Information
Richmond, Virginia woman's activist and state co-coordinator of the Virginia chapter of the National Organization for Women.
Scope and Content
Includes many letters, newspaper clippings, and feminist related items of Zelda Nordlinger, a Richmond, VA woman's activist and state co-coordinator of the Virginia chapter of the National Organization for Women. Includes information on the origins of the National Organization for Women, as well as the Equal Rights Amendment and the abortion issue. Also contains several newsletters published by feminist organizations, pamphlets, photographs, and correspondence with other feminist activists in the state.
Related Materials
Zelda Kingoff Nordlinger Papers, 1970-1983, Library of Virginia. The guide to the collection is available online.
Access Terms
National Organization of Women.; Commission on Status of Women.; Women's International League of Peace and Freedom.; American Civil Liberties Union--History.; Equal Rights Amendment.; Women--Legal status, laws, etc.--United States.
Contents List
- Letters written by Zelda Nordlinger 13 March 1971-19 February 1972, 15 items (Box-folder 1:1)
- Letters, a journal on feminism, and an autobiographical essay written by Zelda Nordlinger. Also includes a copy of the First Richmond Women's Equality Award presented to Zelda Nordlinger. 15 March 1972-13 July 1998, 23 items (Box-folder 1:2)
- Letters, mostly written to Zelda Nordlinger, from political candidates, politicians, and fellow feminists. 3 [November] [19]69-19 April 1970, 14 items (Box-folder 1:3)
- Letters, mostly written to Zelda Nordlinger, from women's activists Holt Carlton and Flora Crater, as well as letters from Gurney W. Grant (manager of a Tea Room in Richmond), United States senators, and others. 9 December 1970-21 [March] [19]71, 15 items (Box-folder 1:4)
- Letters, mostly written to Zelda Nordlinger, from United States senators, Director of Unitarian Universalist Women's Federation Constance Burgess, and others. Includes one letter from Betty Friedan. 6 April 1971-20 August 1971, 18 items (Box-folder 1:5)
- Letters, mostly written to Zelda Nordlinger, from fellow feminists, including political candidate Jane Chittom. Contains many letters of thanks for presentations made by Zelda Nordlinger to such groups as the Fort Lee Officers' Wives Club. Includes an address to the men's Focus Club in Richmond by Holt Carlton. 3 September 1971-18 November 1971, 14 items (Box-folder 1:6)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from the ACLU, United States senators, Associate Editor Overton Jones of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, fellow feminist activists Holt Carlton and Christine Faia, and others. 3 December 1971-27 Feb[ruary] 1972, 11 items (Box-folder 1:7)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from United States senators, political candidates, WWBT TV-12 Broadcasting Company of Virginia, Time Magazine, and feminist activists. Includes an invitation to an event honoring congresswoman Bella Abzug. 4 March 1972-28 Apr[il] [19]72, 18 items (Box-folder 1:8)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from feminist activists including Eleanor Lawrence, Holt Carlton, Genevieve "Genx" Brothers, Meg Williams, and Margaret Talburt, as well as United States senators, and others. 4 May [1972]-30 June 1972, 13 items (Box-folder 1:9)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from feminist activists including Meg Williams, Eleanor Lawrence, Christine Faia, and Genx Brothers, as well as United States senators, the ACLU, the publisher of Women Today, and others. 2 July 1972-27 Sep[tember] 1972, 16 items (Box-folder 1:10)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from feminist activists Holt Carlton, Flora Crater, and Margaret Weatherby, as well as politicians, political candidates, and others. 3 October 1972-9 April 1973, 15 items (Box-folder 1:11)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from the Commission on the Status of Women, Lieutenant Governor of Virginia Henry Howell, the ACLU, the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, as well as United States senators, and others. 12 May 1973-15 December 1973, 15 items (Box-folder 1:12)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from Eileen Freiss of the First Women's Bank, the Unitarian Universalist Women's Federation, Women's Lobby of Virginia, the Prisoner's Solidarity Committee, political candidates, feminist activists, and others. 24 January 1974-5 January 1975, 13 items (Box-folder 1:13)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from the Richmond Times-Dispatch, WTVR radio station, congresswoman Bella Abzug, Richmond Organized Against Rape, the Women's Campaign Fund, United States senators, and feminist activists. 19 March 1975-12 June 1976, 15 items (Box-folder 1:14)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from feminist Flora Crater, Church Women United in Virginia, political candidates, United States senators, and others. Also includes two anonymous letters condemning Zelda Nordlinger for her pro-choice stance on the abortion issue. 6 July 1976-14 July 1998, 14 items (Box-folder 1:15)
- Letters, mostly to Zelda Nordlinger, from the Feminist Press, the Richmond News Leader, feminist activist Eleanor Lawrence, and others. n.d., 10 items (Box-folder 1:16)
- Letters pertaining to the formation of the Richmond chapter of the National Organization for Women. Includes a copy of the Virginia NOW by-laws, a NOW statement of purpose, a summary of the women's movement's early years in Richmond, and other information concerning Virginia NOW's origins. 23 November 1970-September 1973, 17 items (Box-folder 2:1)
- Letters and press releases of the National Organization for Women 25 Feb[ruary] [19]71-7 September 1971, 15 items (Box-folder 2:2)
- Letters and press releases of the National Organization for Women September 1971-20 February 1973, 15 items (Box-folder 2:3)
- Letters and press releases of the National Organization for Women Feb[ruary] 1973-22 [April 1977], 15 items (Box-folder 2:4)
- Newsletters of various chapters of the National Organization for Women September 1970-December 1974, 15 items (Box-folder 2:5)
- Newsletters of various chapters of the National Organization for Women February 1975-May 1998, 13 items (Box-folder 2:6)
- Miscellaneous items pertaining to the National Organization for Women, particularly the Richmond chapter. 17 [February 1971]-1998, 22 items (Box-folder 2:7)
- Copies of The Woman Activist, a bulletin for women's rights, edited by Flora Crater. 15 July 1971-June 1998, 9 items (Box-folder 2:8)
- Newsletters, journals and memos of the Women's Equity Action League and Women's Lobby, Inc. May 1972-3 February 1975, 7 items (Box-folder 2:9)
- Letters, mostly written by Flora Crater, Coordinator of the Virginia Women's Political Caucus, as well as press releases, reports, meeting minutes and newsletters of the Virginia Women's Political Caucus. 2 January 1971-October 1975, 18 items (Box-folder 2:10)
- Letters, newsletters, reports of the National Women's Political Caucus 15 July 1971-February 1976, 12 items (Box-folder 2:11)
- Congressional records, reports of the Commission on the Status of Women, resolutions of the Congress of Women's Organizations in Virginia, and other documents pertaining to the status of women. 10 March 1971-1983, 10 items (Box-folder 2:12)
- Papers pertaining to the Equal Rights Amendment. Includes many letters from United States senators and reports of the Citizens' Advisory Council. 27 August 1970-16 March 1972, 20 items (Box-folder 2:13)
- Papers pertaining to the Equal Rights Amendment. Includes letters, fliers, etc. 24 March 1972-8 November 1973, 20 items (Box-folder 2:14)
- Papers pertaining to the Equal Rights Amendment. Includes reports of the Virginia ERA Ratification Council, letters, brochures, etc. 2 December 1974-December 1995, 22 items (Box-folder 2:15)
- Papers pertaining to the abortion issue and family planning. Includes Planned Parenthood-World Population Memos, abortion fact sheets, etc. May 1967-15 January 1976, 20 items (Box-folder 2:16)
- Newspaper clippings 26 October 1969-23 March 1972, 30 items (Box-folder 3:1)
- Newspaper clippings 24 March 1972-28 December 1972, 30 items (Box-folder 3:2)
- Newspaper clippings 3 January 1973-24 August 1973, 30 items (Box-folder 3:3)
- Newspaper clippings 24 August 1973-29 March 1974, 30 items (Box-folder 3:4)
- Newspaper clippings 2 May 1974-6 March 1975, 30 items (Box-folder 3:5)
- Newspaper clippings 30 March 1975-18 July 1975, 30 items (Box-folder 3:6)
- Newspaper clippings 21 July 1975-14 November 1975, 30 items (Box-folder 3:7)
- Newspaper clippings 30 November 1975-21 March 1976, 30 items (Box-folder 3:8)
- Newspaper clippings 21 1976-19 August 1976, 30 items (Box-folder 3:9)
- Newspaper clippings 19 August 1976-8 January 1977, 30 items (Box-folder 3:10)
- Newspaper clippings 11 January 1977-4 May 1977, 31 items (Box-folder 3:11)
- Newspaper clippings 23 May 1977-19 August 1982, 30 items (Box-folder 3:12)
- Newspaper clippings September 1982-23 July 1983, 30 items (Box-folder 3:13)
- Newspaper clippings 28 July 1983-11 November 1983, 30 items (Box-folder 3:14)
- Newspaper clippings 11 November 1983-13 January 1985, 30 items (Box-folder 3:15)
- Newspaper clippings 5 May 1985-18 May 1990, 30 items (Box-folder 3:16)
- Newspaper clippings n.d., 35 items (Box-folder 3:17)
- Newspaper clippings n.d., 37 items (Box-folder 3:18)
- "The Right to Abortion: A Psychiatric View," published by the Group for the Advancement of Psychiatry October 1969, 1 item (Box-folder 3:19)
- Newspapers 3 March 1971-December 1972, 3 items (Box-folder 3:20)
- Newspapers 14 November 1973-November 1975, 4 items (Box-folder 3:21)
- Newspapers 30 August 1976-13 January 1980, 3 items (Box-folder 3:22)
- The Plain Truth, A Magazine of Understanding September 1981, 1 item (Box-folder 3:23)
- Newspapers 14 April 1983-15 October 1983, 3 items (Box-folder 3:24)
- Newspapers 20 October 1985-1998, 4 items (Box-folder 3:25)
- Time Magazine 29 June 1998, 1 item (Box-folder 3:26)
- Miscellaneous, 29 items (Box-folder 3:27)
- Miscellaneous, 31 items (Box-folder 3:28)
- Miscellaneous, 28 items (Box-folder 3:29)
- Pamphlets, including those distributed by National Organization for Women, Women's Campaign Fund, American Civil Liberties Union, Women's International League of Peace and Freedom, and others. n.d., 25 items (Box-folder 3:30)
- Photographs n.d., 17 items (Box-folder 3:31)
  P1. Bradford, Lynn
  P2. Bradford, Lynn and women--unidentified
  P3. Bradford, Lynn and Gretchen Roberts, Carla Bradshaw
  P4. Carlton, Mary Holt
  P5. Carlton, Mary Holt
  P6. Lawrence, Eleanor
  P7. Nordlinger, Zelda
  P8. Nordlinger, Zelda and Debbie Markel, Juanita White
  P9. Nordlinger, Zelda and Michele Hensley, Betty Meridith, Hope Montoni
  P10. Nordlinger, Zelda and Mary Holt Carlton
  P11. Nordlinger, Zelda and women--unidentified
  P12. Roberts, Gretchen
  P13. National Organization for Women Conference--Philadelphia
  P14. N.O.W. Conference--Philadelphia or New York
  P15. N.O.W. Conference--Philadelphia or New York
  P16. N.O.W. Conference--New York?
  P17. N.O.W. Conference